<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<refentry lang="en">
<refentryinfo>
    <title>ansible-vault(1)</title>
</refentryinfo>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>ansible-vault</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source">Ansible</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">System administration commands</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="version"></refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
    <refname>ansible-vault</refname>
    <refpurpose>manage encrypted ansible vars files (YAML).</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id="_synopsis">
<simpara>ansible-vault [create|decrypt|edit|encrypt|rekey] [--help] [options] file_name</simpara>
</refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1 id="_description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">ansible-vault</emphasis> can encrypt any structured data file used by Ansible.
This can include <emphasis role="strong">group_vars/</emphasis> or <emphasis role="strong">host_vars/</emphasis> inventory variables,
variables loaded by <emphasis role="strong">include_vars</emphasis> or <emphasis role="strong">vars_files</emphasis>, or variable files
passed on the ansible-playbook command line with <emphasis role="strong">-e @file.yml</emphasis> or <emphasis role="strong">-e @file.json</emphasis>.
Role variables and defaults are also included!</simpara>
<simpara>Because Ansible tasks, handlers, and so on are also data, these can also be encrypted with vault.
If you’d like to not betray what variables you are even using, you can go as far to keep an individual task file entirely encrypted.</simpara>
<simpara>The password used with vault currently must be the same for all files you wish to use together at the same time.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_common_options">
<title>COMMON OPTIONS</title>
<simpara>The following options are available to all sub-commands:</simpara>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis role="strong">--vault-password-file=</emphasis><emphasis>FILE</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
A file containing the vault password to be used during the encryption/decryption
steps. Be sure to keep this file secured if it is used. If the file is executable,
it will be run and its standard output will be used as the password.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis role="strong">--new-vault-password-file=</emphasis><emphasis>FILE</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
A file containing the new vault password to be used when rekeying a
file. Be sure to keep this file secured if it is used. If the file
is executable, it will be run and its standard output will be used as
the password.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<emphasis role="strong">-h</emphasis>, <emphasis role="strong">--help</emphasis>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Show a help message related to the given sub-command.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<simpara>If <emphasis>--valut-password-file</emphasis> is not supplied ansib-vault will automatically prompt for passwords as required.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_create">
<title>CREATE</title>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault create [options] FILE</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">create</emphasis> sub-command is used to initialize a new encrypted file.</simpara>
<simpara>After providing a password, the tool will launch whatever editor you have defined
with $EDITOR, and defaults to vim. Once you are done with the editor session, the
file will be saved as encrypted data.</simpara>
<simpara>The default cipher is AES (which is shared-secret based).</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_edit">
<title>EDIT</title>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault edit [options] FILE</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">edit</emphasis> sub-command is used to modify a file which was previously encrypted using ansible-vault.</simpara>
<simpara>This command will decrypt the file to a temporary file and allow you to edit the file,
saving it back when done and removing the temporary file.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_rekey">
<title>REKEY</title>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault rekey [options] FILE_1 [FILE_2, &#8230;, FILE_N]</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">rekey</emphasis> command is used to change the password on a vault-encrypted files.
This command can update multiple files at once.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_encrypt">
<title>ENCRYPT</title>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault encrypt [options] FILE_1 [FILE_2, &#8230;, FILE_N]</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">encrypt</emphasis> sub-command is used to encrypt pre-existing data files.
As with the <emphasis role="strong">rekey</emphasis> command, you can specify multiple files in one command.</simpara>
<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">encrypt</emphasis> command accepts an <emphasis role="strong">--output FILENAME</emphasis> option to determine where
encrypted output is stored. With this option, input is read from the (at most one)
filename given on the command line; if no input file is given, input is read from stdin.
Either the input or the output file may be given as <emphasis>-</emphasis> for stdin and stdout respectively.
If neither input nor output file is given, the command acts as a filter,
reading plaintext from stdin and writing it to stdout.</simpara>
<simpara>Thus any of the following invocations can be used:</simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault encrypt</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault encrypt --output OUTFILE</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault encrypt INFILE --output OUTFILE</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ echo secret|ansible-vault encrypt --output OUTFILE</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara>Reading from stdin and writing only encrypted output is a good way to prevent
sensitive data from ever hitting disk (either interactively or from a script).</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_decrypt">
<title>DECRYPT</title>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">$ ansible-vault decrypt [options] FILE_1 [FILE_2, &#8230;, FILE_N]</emphasis></simpara>
<simpara>The <emphasis role="strong">decrypt</emphasis> sub-command is used to remove all encryption from data files.
The files will be stored as plain-text YAML once again, so be sure that you do not run this
command on data files with active passwords or other sensitive data.
In most cases, users will want to use the <emphasis role="strong">edit</emphasis> sub-command to modify the files securely.</simpara>
<simpara>As with <emphasis role="strong">encrypt</emphasis>, the <emphasis role="strong">decrypt</emphasis> subcommand also accepts the <emphasis role="strong">--output FILENAME</emphasis>
option to specify where plaintext output is stored, and stdin/stdout is handled
as described above.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_author">
<title>AUTHOR</title>
<simpara>Ansible was originally written by Michael DeHaan. See the AUTHORS file
for a complete list of contributors.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_copyright">
<title>COPYRIGHT</title>
<simpara>Copyright © 2014, Michael DeHaan</simpara>
<simpara>Ansible is released under the terms of the GPLv3 License.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_see_also">
<title>SEE ALSO</title>
<simpara><emphasis role="strong">ansible</emphasis>(1), <emphasis role="strong">ansible-pull</emphasis>(1), <emphasis role="strong">ansible-doc</emphasis>(1), <emphasis role="strong">ansible-playbook</emphasis>(1), <emphasis role="strong">ansible-galaxy</emphasis>(1)</simpara>
<simpara>Extensive documentation is available in the documentation site:
<ulink url="http://docs.ansible.com">http://docs.ansible.com</ulink>. IRC and mailing list info can be found
in file CONTRIBUTING.md, available in: <ulink url="https://github.com/ansible/ansible">https://github.com/ansible/ansible</ulink></simpara>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
