<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="timesyncd.conf" conditional="ENABLE_TIMESYNCD">
  <info>
    
    <productname>systemd</productname>

    <authorgroup>
      <author><personname><firstname>Lennart</firstname><surname>Poettering</surname></personname><contrib>Developer</contrib><email>lennart@poettering.net</email></author>
    </authorgroup>
  </info>

  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>timesyncd.conf</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
  </refmeta>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>timesyncd.conf</refname>
    <refname>timesyncd.conf.d</refname>
    <refpurpose>Network Time Synchronization configuration files</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para><filename>/etc/systemd/timesyncd.conf</filename></para>
    <para><filename>/etc/systemd/timesyncd.conf.d/*.conf</filename></para>
    <para><filename>/run/systemd/timesyncd.conf.d/*.conf</filename></para>
    <para><filename>/usr/lib/systemd/timesyncd.conf.d/*.conf</filename></para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>

    <para>These configuration files control NTP network time
    synchronization.</para>

  </refsect1>

  <refsection xml:id="main-conf">
    <title>Configuration Directories and Precedence</title>

    <para>Default configuration is defined during compilation, so a
    configuration file is only needed when it is necessary to deviate
    from those defaults. By default the configuration file in
    <filename>/etc/systemd/</filename> contains commented out entries
    showing the defaults as a guide to the administrator. This file
    can be edited to create local overrides.
    </para>

    <para>When packages need to customize the configuration, they can
    install configuration snippets in
    <filename>/usr/lib/systemd/*.conf.d/</filename>. Files in
    <filename>/etc/</filename> are reserved for the local
    administrator, who may use this logic to override the
    configuration files installed by vendor packages. The main
    configuration file is read before any of the configuration
    directories, and has the lowest precedence; entries in a file in
    any configuration directory override entries in the single
    configuration file. Files in the
    <filename>*.conf.d/</filename> configuration subdirectories
    are sorted by their filename in lexicographic order, regardless of
    which of the subdirectories they reside in. If multiple files
    specify the same option, the entry in the file with the
    lexicographically latest name takes precedence.  It is recommended
    to prefix all filenames in those subdirectories with a two-digit
    number and a dash, to simplify the ordering of the files.</para>

    <para>To disable a configuration file supplied by the vendor, the
    recommended way is to place a symlink to
    <filename>/dev/null</filename> in the configuration directory in
    <filename>/etc/</filename>, with the same filename as the vendor
    configuration file.</para>
  </refsection>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>

    <variablelist class="network-directives">

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>NTP=</varname></term>
        <listitem><para>A space separated list of NTP servers host
        names or IP addresses. During runtime this list is combined
        with any per-interface NTP servers acquired from
        <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-networkd.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>.
        systemd-timesyncd will contact all configured system or
        per-interface servers in turn until one is found that
        responds. This setting defaults to the empty
        list.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><varname>FallbackNTP=</varname></term>
        <listitem><para>A space separated list of NTP server host
        names or IP addresses to be used as the fallback NTP servers.
        Any per-interface NTP servers obtained from
        <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-networkd.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
        take precedence over this setting, as do any servers set via
        <varname>NTP=</varname> above. This setting is hence only used
        if no other NTP server information is known. If this option is
        not given, a compiled-in list of NTP servers is used
        instead.</para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
      <title>See Also</title>
      <para>
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-timesyncd.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
      <citerefentry><refentrytitle>systemd-networkd.service</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
      </para>
  </refsect1>

</refentry>