<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>OPENSSL_instrument_bus.pod</refentrytitle>
  </refmeta>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>OPENSSL_instrument_bus, OPENSSL_instrument_bus2</refname>
<refpurpose>instrument references to memory bus</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
<synopsis format="linespecific">#ifdef OPENSSL_CPUID_OBJ
size_t OPENSSL_instrument_bus (int *vector,size_t num);
size_t OPENSSL_instrument_bus2(int *vector,size_t num,size_t max);
#endif</synopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
  <refsection xml:id="sources.openssl.doc.crypto.OPENSSL_instrument_bus.pod:DESCRIPTION"><title>DESCRIPTION</title>
    <para>
      It was empirically found that timings of references to primary memory
      are subject to irregular, apparently non-deterministic variations.
      The subroutines in question instrument these references for purposes
      of gathering entropy for random number generator. In order to make it
      bus-bound a 'flush cache line' instruction is used between probes. In
      addition probes are added to <emphasis role="bold">vector</emphasis>
      elements in atomic or interlocked manner, which should contribute
      additional noise on multi-processor systems. This also means that
      <emphasis role="bold">vector[num]</emphasis> should be zeroed upon
      invocation (if you want to retrieve actual probe values).
    </para>
    <para>
      OPENSSL_instrument_bus performs <emphasis role="bold">num</emphasis>
      probes and records the number of oscillator cycles every probe took.
    </para>
    <para>
      OPENSSL_instrument_bus2 on the other hand <emphasis role="bold">accumulates</emphasis> consecutive probes with the same
      value, i.e. in a way it records duration of periods when probe values
      appeared deterministic. The subroutine performs at most <emphasis role="bold">max</emphasis> probes in attempt to fill the <emphasis role="bold">vector[num]</emphasis>, with <emphasis role="bold">max</emphasis> value of 0 meaning "as many as it takes."
    </para>
  </refsection>
  <refsection xml:id="sources.openssl.doc.crypto.OPENSSL_instrument_bus.pod:RETURN_VALUE"><title>RETURN VALUE</title>
    <para>
      Return value of 0 indicates that CPU is not capable of performing the
      benchmark, either because oscillator counter or 'flush cache line' is
      not available on current platform. For reference, on x86 'flush cache
      line' was introduced with the SSE2 extensions.
    </para>
    <para>
      Otherwise number of recorded values is returned.
    </para>
  </refsection>
</refentry>