<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.1 -->
<refentry xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
<info>
    
</info>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>xisetfocus</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>3</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source"> </refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual"> </refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
    <refname>XISetFocus</refname>
    <refname>XIGetFocus</refname>
    <refpurpose>set or get the device's focus.</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv xml:id="_synopsis">
<literallayout class="monospaced">#include &lt;X11/extensions/XInput2.h&gt;</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">Status XISetFocus( Display *display,
                   int deviceid,
                   Window focus,
                   Time time);</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">Status XIGetFocus( Display *display,
                   Window *focus_return);</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">display
       Specifies the connection to the X server.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">deviceid
       Specifies the device whose focus is to be queried or
       changed.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">focus
       The new focus window.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">focus_return
       Returns the current focus window.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">time
       A valid timestamp or CurrentTime.</literallayout>
</refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1 xml:id="_description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<literallayout class="monospaced">XISetFocus changes the focus of the specified device ans its
last-focus-change time. It has no effect if the specified time
is earlier than the current last-focus-change time or is later
than the current X server time. Otherwise, the
last-focus-change time is set to the specified time.
CurrentTime is replaced by the current X server time).
XISetFocus causes the X server to generate core, XI and XI2
focus events.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">If the focus window is None all keyboard events by this device
are discarded until a new focus window is set. Otherwise, if
focus is a window, it becomes the device's focus window. If a
generated device event would normally be reported to this
window or one of its inferiors, the event is reported as usual.
Otherwise, the event is reported relative to the focus window.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">The specified focus window must be viewable at the time
XISetFocus is called, or a BadMatch error results. If the focus
window later becomes not viewable, the focus reverts to the
parent (or the closest viewable ancestor. When the focus
reverts, the X server generates core, XI and XI2 focus events
but the last-focus-change time is not affected.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">Attempting to set the focus on a master pointer device or an
attached slave device will result in a BadDevice error.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">XISetFocus can generate BadDevice, BadMatch, BadValue, and
BadWindow errors.</literallayout>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 xml:id="_diagnostics">
<title>DIAGNOSTICS</title>
<literallayout class="monospaced">BadValue
       A value is outside of the permitted range.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">BadDevice
       An invalid device was specified. The device does not
       exist or is not a appropriate for the type of change.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">BadMatch
       The window is not viewable.</literallayout>
<literallayout class="monospaced">BadWindow
       A value for a Window argument does not name a defined
       Window.</literallayout>
</refsect1>
</refentry>